This video is about Medicare and Durable
Medical Equipment, or DME. Let’s get started!
DME is equipment that helps you with your
activities of daily living, such as getting in and
out of bed, bathing, using the toilet, and eating.
Not every type of DME is eligible for Medicare
coverage. Medicare usually covers DME that is
durable, meaning it can withstand repeated use,
serves a medical purpose, is appropriate for use
in the home, although it may also be used outside,
and is likely to last for three years or more.
For example, Medicare covers wheelchairs,
walkers, hospital beds, power scooters,
and portable oxygen equipment.
Medicare also covers prosthetics, orthotics,
and certain medical supplies as DME.
On the other hand, there are certain kinds of DME
that Medicare never covers.
Let’s look at some examples.
Medicare doesn’t cover equipment that’s
mainly used to help you outside the home.
For example, if you can walk on your own for
short distances and get around your house,
Medicare wouldn’t cover a motorized scooter
that you only need outside the home.
Second, Medicare doesn’t cover most equipment used
to make things more convenient or comfortable.
This includes stairway elevators, grab
bars, air conditioners, and toilet seats.
Medicare also doesn’t cover items that get
thrown away after being used or that aren’t used
with equipment. For example, Medicare doesn’t
cover incontinence pads, surgical facemasks,
or compression leggings, unless these items are
covered as part of your home health benefit.
Additionally, Medicare won’t
cover modifications to your home,
such as ramps or widened doors
for improving wheelchair access.
Whether you have Original Medicare or a Medicare
Advantage Plan, Medicare covers your DME if
you meet the following two conditions. First,
your primary care provider must sign an order,
prescription, or certificate. Second, you must
take your prescription to the right supplier.
Be sure only to use suppliers with approval from
Original Medicare or your Medicare Advantage Plan.
It’s important to note, however, that the
process is a little different if you need a
manual or power wheelchair or scooter. In these
cases, speak with your primary care provider.
In most cases, Medicare Part B covers your DME.
Medicare normally pays eighty percent of the
Medicare-approved amount after you meet your Part
B deductible. This means you would owe a twenty
percent coinsurance for your DME if the supplier
charges the Medicare-approved amount for the item.
To find a DME supplier that’s approved by
Medicare, visit www.medicare.gov/supplier.
Be aware that many suppliers are Medicare-approved
but don’t “take assignment.” If a provider doesn’t
take assignment, that means they don’t accept the
Medicare-approved amount as the full payment for
the item. These suppliers may charge more, but
Medicare will still only pay eighty percent of
its approved amount, so you’ll be responsible for
the twenty percent coinsurance plus any charges
above the Medicare-approved amount. If you have
a Medicare Advantage Plan, your plan will have
its own cost and coverage rules for DME. You
should contact your plan for more information.
In conclusion, if you need Medicare-covered
DME, take the following steps.
Work with your primary care provider to get
a prescription for medically necessary DME.
Contact Medicare or your Medicare Advantage Plan
to get a list of DME suppliers in your area that
would provide you with the lowest costs. And
take your DME prescription to a supplier.
That concludes this video on Medicare and
Durable Medical Equipment. Thanks for watching.